A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Research Division, Office Files of Fred E. Crossland FA713
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Research Division, Office Files of Fred E. Crossland
1970-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Crossland, Fred E. (Fred Eugene), 1920-
Ford Foundation
FA713
4.84 Cubic Feet
The Education and Research Papers of Fred E. Crossland were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982. These papers consist primarily of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, Venture Fund Program materials, and American Undergraduate Education files. They are divided into two series: Education Files and Correspondence Files. Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Crossland's office.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned reports. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
Fred E. Crossland, Ford Foundation Program Officer in the Division of Education and Research (ER), was a member of the Foundation staff from 1964 until 1981. During this period, he held the following positions:
October 1977, Program Officer, ER
September 1971, Program Officer, Office of Higher Education and Research, ER
January 1967, Program Officer, Special Projects in Education, ER
March 1964, Program Associate, EP
Fred Crossland was born October 3, 1920. He received his A.B. degree in 1942 in History from Brooklyn College. In 1947 and 1953 respectively, he earned his A.M. and Ph.D. degrees in History from New York University.
Prior to Crossland's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
1947-1964, New York University:
Dean of Admissions
Assistant Secretary and Director of Public Relations
Assistant Director of Advisement, School of
Commerce, Accounts and Finance
Instructor of History; Assistant Professor of Political Science, University College of Arts and Sciences and the School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance
After his retirement from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Crossland held two positions: Vice President of the W. Alton Jones Foundation of Charlottesville, Virginia; and Research Professor and Special Assistant to the Provost, Duke University, at Durham, North Carolina.
Scope and Contents
These papers, which consist of eleven boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, reports, and a draft of the Crossland publication The Changing American College, are primarily concerned with the application process of the Venture Fund Program, the American Undergraduate Education survey, and, to a lesser extent, with the issues facing educators on the college level in the 1970's.
The papers reflect Crossland's involvement during the years 1973-74 with the Foundation-sponsored Venture Fund Program. Initiated in 1970, the Venture Fund Program sought to respond to the student unrest of the late 1960's, by helping to strengthen, and to encourage innovation in, undergraduate education in America.
The files consist of completed questionnaires, related correspondence, and accounts of site visits by FF staff to institutions applying for Venture Fund grants.
The October 1974 American Undergraduate Education survey, a follow-up to the Venture Fund Program, solicited responses from eighty-nine educators who were asked to identify what they thought were the major issues and problems facing America's colleges and universities at that time.
The American Undergraduate Education survey material consists of completed questionnaires, related correspondence, and mini-profiles of the responding institutions.
The papers contain a draft of Crossland's book, The Changing American College, in which he discussed the state of American higher education based upon conclusions drawn from the Venture Fund Program and the American Undergraduate Education survey.
One box of material relates to educational planning for the 1980's. This correspondence, which Crossland maintained with top college and university officials in thirteen states, deals mainly with the problem of decreasing student enrollment and its affect on state university systems.
Crossland maintained an array of subject files, all related to FF educational concerns: fellowship programs for minority students, Higher Education and Research planning and budget material, and material on the issues facing the financing of American higher education. There are also the transcripts of seven speeches which Crossland made to various professional organizations and meetings.
Finally, there is the correspondence he maintained with FF colleagues, grantees, and other educational organizations; and Crossland's notes to the "File."
Arrangement
The Education and Research Papers of Fred E. Crossland are divided into two series:
I. Education Files II. Correspondence Files
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Education Files, 1970-1980; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Education Files (1970-1980), is the most substantive and extensive. It contains material on the activities of the Division of Education and Research. Of particular interest is the memoranda, site visit reports, and related documentation concerning the Venture Fund Program; and the correspondence and other related material dealing with the American Undergraduate Education survey.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into the following five sub-series:
  A. Venture Fund Program Information and Questionnaire Responses (2 boxes) B. Venture Fund Program Site Visits (1.5 boxes) C. American Undergraduate Education Survey Files (1.5 boxes) D. Planning for the 1980's (1 box) E. Subject Files (1.5 boxes)
  Within each folder, the material is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Venture Fund Program Information and Questionnaire Responses, A
    These files consist of Venture Fund Program application materials and correspondence. They are arranged alphabetically by name of institution. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Venture Fund Program Background Information (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adelphi University, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Albright College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alfred University, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Allegheny College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alliance College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Amherst College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Anna Maria College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Assumption College, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bard College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Barnard College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Barrington College, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baruch College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bates College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bennington College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bentley College, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Boston College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Boston State College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Boston University, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bowdoin College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bradford College, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - University of Bridgeport, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Brown University, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bryn Mawr College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Bucknell University, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - California State College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Canisius College, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Carnegie Mellon University, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Castelton State College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Cedar Crest College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Chatham College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - City College of New York, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Clarkson College of Technology, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Colby College (Maine), 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Colby College (New Hampshire), 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Colegio Universidad del Turabo, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Colgate University, 1974 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - College of the Atlantic, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - College of Holy Cross, 1973 November-December (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - College of New Rochelle, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - College of White Plains, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - College of St. Rose, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - College of the Sacred Heart, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Columbia College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Columbia University, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Connecticut College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Cornell University, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Curry College, 1974 April-May (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Dickinson College, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Douglass College (Rutgers), 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Dowling College, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Duquesne University, 1974 April-May (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - D'Youville College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - E. Stroudsburg St. College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - E. Connecticut St. College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Eisenhower College, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Elmira College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Empire State College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Fordham University, 1974 January-February (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Franconia College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Franklin & Marshall College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Friends World College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Goddard College, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Hampshire College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - University of Hartford, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Hartwick College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Harvard University, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Hobart & Wm. Smith College, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Hofstra University, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Immaculata College, 1974 January-February (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Ithaca College, 1973 November-December (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Johnson State College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Juniata College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - King's College, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Kirkland College, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Lafayette College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - La Roche College, 1973 November-December (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - La Salle College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Lehigh University, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Herbert H. Lehman College, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Le Moyne College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Lebanon Valley College, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Lock Haven State College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Long Island University, 1974 April 25-May 3 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Long Island University, 1974 January 23-28 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - University of Maine (Farmington), 1974 March-April (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - University of Maine (Orono), 1973 November-December (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - University of Maine (Portland), 1973 February-March (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - University of Maine (Presque Is.), 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Manhattan College, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Manhattanville College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Mansfield State College, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Marist College, 1974 May (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Marlboro College, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Marymount Manhattan College, 1974 April (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Marywood College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Medgar Evans College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Mercy College, 1974 April-May (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Mercyhurst College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Messiah College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Middlebury College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - College Misericordia, 1973 December-1974 January (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Montclair State College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Moravian College, 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Mount Holyoke College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Muhlenberg College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - New England College, 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - University of New Hampshire, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - University of New Haven, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - N.Y. Institute of Technology, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - New York University, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Nichols College, 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Pace University, 1974 April - March (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Pennsylvania State University, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - University of Pittsburg, 1974 April (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Pratt Institute, 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Princeton University, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Providence College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Queens College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Quinnipiac College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Ramapo College, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Rensselaer Polytechnic Inst., 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Richmond College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Rider College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Robert Morris College, 1974 March - February (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Roger Williams College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Rosary Hill College, 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Russell Sage College, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Sacred Heart College, 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - St. Bonaventure University, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - St. John Fisher College, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - St. Lawrence University, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - St. Michael's College, 1974 May (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - St. Peters College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - St. Thomas Aquinas College, 1974 February - January (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Sarah Lawrence College, 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - School for International Training, 1974 February - January (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - University of Scranton, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 139)
    - Seton Hall College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - Seton Hall University, 1974 February - January (Box 2, Folder 141)
    - Shippensburg State College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - Skidmore College, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - Smith College, 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 144)
    - Springfield College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - St. Univ. Coll. at Utica/Rome, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - SUNY (Albany), 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 147)
    - SUNY (Binghamton), 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 148)
    - SUNY (Brockport), 1974 January - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 149)
    - SUNY (Geneseo), 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 150)
    - SUNY (New Paltz), 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 151)
    - SUNY (Potsdam), 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 152)
    - Stevens Inst. of Technology, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 153)
    - Stockton State College, 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 154)
    - Stonehill College, 1974 February - January (Box 2, Folder 155)
    - Susquehanna University, 1973 December - November (Box 2, Folder 156)
    - Swarthmore College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 157)
    - Syracuse University, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 158)
    - Temple University, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 159)
    - Trinity College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 160)
    - Tufts University, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 161)
    - Union College, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 162)
    - Upsala College, 1974 April (Box 2, Folder 163)
    - University Of Vermont, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 164)
    - Villa Maria College, 1974 February - 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 165)
    - Villanova University, 1974 March (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Wagner College, 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 167)
    - Washington & Jefferson Coll., 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 168)
    - Waynesburg College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 169)
    - Wellesley College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 170)
    - Wells College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - Wesleyan University, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 172)
    - Wheaton College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - Widener College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Wilkes College, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 175)
    - Wilson College, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 176)
    - Worcester Polytechnic Inst., 1973 November (Box 2, Folder 177)
    - Yale University, 1974 May (Box 2, Folder 178)
    - Yeshiva University, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 179)
  - Venture Fund Program Site Visits, B
    This sub-series is further divided into four sections: Venture Fund Program Northeast, Venture Fund Program Midwest, Venture Fund Program South, and the August 1974 Venture Fund Program Conference at Nordic Hills. Arrangement of the files is by geographic location, and within each folder, alphabetical by name of institution. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Northeast
      - Venture Fund N.E. - Information, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 180)
      - Alfred University, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 181)
      - Amherst College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 182)
      - Bates College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 183)
      - Bennington College, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 184)
      - Bentley College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 185)
      - Boston College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 186)
      - Boston University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 187)
      - Bowdoin College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 188)
      - Brown University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 189)
      - Bryn Mawr College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 190)
      - Carnegie Mellon University, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 191)
      - Castelton State College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 192)
      - Chatham College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 193)
      - Colby College, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 194)
      - College of the Atlantic, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 195)
      - Columbia University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 196)
      - Cornell University, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 197)
      - E. Connecticut State College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 198)
      - Elmira College, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 199)
      - Empire State College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 200)
      - Goddard College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 201)
      - University of Hartford, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 202)
      - Harvard University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 203)
      - Hobart & Wm. Smith College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 204)
      - Immaculate Heart College, 1973 July (Box 3, Folder 205)
      - La Roche College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 206)
      - Lehigh University, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 207)
      - Manhattan College, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 208)
      - Manhattanville College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 209)
      - Mansfield State College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 210)
      - Mercyhurst College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 211)
      - Messiah College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 212)
      - Middlebury College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 213)
      - College Misericordia, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 214)
      - Mount Holyoke College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 215)
      - University of New Hampshire, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 216)
      - Pace University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 217)
      - University of Pennsylvania, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 218)
      - University of Pittsburg, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 219)
      - Princeton University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 220)
      - Providence College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 221)
      - St. Lawrence University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 222)
      - Sarah Lawrence College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 223)
      - School for Inter. Training, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 224)
      - Skidmore College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 225)
      - SUNY (Albany), 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 226)
      - SUNY (Binghamton), 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 227)
      - SUNY (Potsdam), 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 228)
      - Stevens Inst. of Technology, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 229)
      - Stonehill College, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 230)
      - Swarthmore College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 231)
      - Trinity College, 1974 January (Box 3, Folder 232)
      - University of Vermont, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 233)
      - Wellesley College, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 234)
      - Wesleyan University, 1974 May (Box 3, Folder 235)
      - Widener College, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 236)
      - Wilson College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 237)
      - Worcester Polytechnic Inst, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 238)
    - Midwest
      - Venture Fund Program Midwest - Information (Box 3, Folder 239)
      - Alverno College, 1972 December (Box 3, Folder 240)
      - Carleton College, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 241)
      - Case Western Reserve University, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 242)
      - University of Cincinnati, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 243)
      - Coe College, 1973 May (Box 3, Folder 244)
      - College of St. Thomas, 1972 October (Box 3, Folder 245)
      - Earlham College, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 246)
      - Edgewood College, 1972 November (Box 3, Folder 247)
      - Grand Valley St. College, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 248)
      - Hamline University, 1972 October (Box 3, Folder 249)
      - Hiram College, 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 250)
      - Hope College, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 251)
      - Kent State University, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 252)
      - Kenyon College, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 253)
      - Lawrence University, 1972 November (Box 3, Folder 254)
      - Macalester College, 1972 October (Box 3, Folder 255)
      - MacMurray College, 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 256)
      - Michigan State University, 1973 May (Box 3, Folder 257)
      - University of Minnesota, 1972 October (Box 3, Folder 258)
      - Minnesota Metropolitan St. Coll., 1973 May (Box 3, Folder 259)
      - Mundelein College, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 260)
      - Oberlin College, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 261)
      - Otterbein College, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 262)
      - Roosevelt University, 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 263)
      - Sangamon State University, 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 264)
      - Univ. of Wisconsin (Green Bay), 1972 November (Box 3, Folder 265)
      - Univ. of Wisconsin (Madison), 1972 December (Box 3, Folder 266)
      - Univ. of Wisconsin (Milwaukee), 1972 December (Box 3, Folder 267)
    - South
      - Venture Fund Program South - Information (Box 4, Folder 268)
      - University of Alabama, 1970 October - January (Box 4, Folder 269)
      - Alderson Broaddus College, 1971 September - August (Box 4, Folder 270)
      - American University, 1971 October - March (Box 4, Folder 271)
      - Appalachian State University, 1971 April (Box 4, Folder 272)